Guide to the Ray June papers, 1915-1958.
June, Ray papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Ray June papers, 1915-1958.
2588
Ray June 1898-1958.
.4 cubic ft.
Photographs
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Photographs of movie scenes, crews, casts, and directors of the many motion pictures June filmed for Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer and other companies.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Cinematographer, nicknamed “the ace cameraman of MGM,” and singled out in 1939 by pioneer film historian Lewis Jacobs as one of America's finest cinematographers. Born in Ithaca, N.Y., June attended Columbia University (evidently without graduating). He served as a cameraman in the US Army Signal Corps in World War I, and then moved to Hollywood after the war to embark on a career in cinematography. In the 1920s, he was the cameraman for a “Rin-Tin-Tin” film, and throughout the 1930s and 1940s, he continued to turn out works of distinction at both Goldwyn and MGM studios. He was nominated for an Academy Award three times, in 1932, 1935, and 1957.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Photographs of movie scenes, crews, casts, and directors of the many motion pictures June filmed for Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer and other companies; photos of June; three certificates (1932, 1935, 1957) of nominations for the cinematography award from the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences; and personal items. Included are photos of Myrna Loy, Esther Williams, Lana Turner, Jean Harlow, Robert Montgomery, William Powell, the Marx Brothers, Gloria Swanson, Audrey Hepburn, Judy Garland, Mickey Rooney, Hedy Lamarr, Rosalind Russell, June Allyson, Dick Powell, Mary Pickford, Clark Gable, and other actors, actresses, and film makers.
SUBJECTS
Names:
June, Ray, 1898-1958.; Allyson, June, 1917-2006.; Gable, Clark, 1901-1960.; Garland, Judy.; Harlow, Jean, 1911-1937.; Hepburn, Audrey, 1929-1993.; Lamarr, Hedy, 1913-2000.; Loy, Myrna, 1905-1993.; Montgomery, Robert, 1904-1981.; Pickford, Mary, 1892-1979.; Powell, Dick.; Powell, William, 1892-1984.; Rin Tin Tin, (Dog); Rooney, Mickey.; Russell, Rosalind.; Swanson, Gloria.; Turner, Lana, 1921-1995.; Williams, Esther.; Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences.; Marx Brothers.; Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer.
Subjects:
Cinematography.; Motion picture actors and actresses -- California -- Los Angeles.; Cinematographers -- United States.
Places:
Hollywood (Los Angeles, Calif.)
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- "Now or Never", 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "Night Must Fall", Lew Ayers, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "Gigi", Louis Jourdan, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Jean Harlow and June, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "Above and Beyond", cast and crew, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Mary Pickford ("Secrets"?), ca. 1933 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "Reformer and The Red Head", cast and crew, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Rin Tin Tin ("The Phantom of The Forest"?), ca. 1926 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Sporting Age", train scene, June behind camera, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "Strike Up The Band", Judy Garland and Mickey Rooney, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Ziegfeld Girl", Judy Garland, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "Funny Face", photos of Paris set including Audrey Hepburn, Montmartre, entrence to Louvre, Eiffel Tower, Paris Opera House, Champs Elysses, Goose Bay, Labrador Airport, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "Indiscreet", including Gloria Swanson with Leo McCarey, Adm. Byrd, Ben Lyon and June, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- "And One Was Beautiful", 1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Montage with Marx Brothers and others, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Lana Turner and June, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Photos from set of "Easy To Love", including Esther Williams, 100 female swimmers, and color picture of June in rowboat, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Myrna Loy, William Powell, June and others with birthday cake, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Robert Montgomery, Myrna Loy, June ("When Ladies Meet"?), ca. 1933 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- "Death In a Doll House", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- "Callaway Went That Way", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- "H.M. Pullman Esq.", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Several unidentified photographs, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Glossy and dull prints of June as a young, middle aged, and older man, both on and off sets, sometimes with other crewmen, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  -includes 1 color photo and 1 photo of a young man dated 1915, which may not be June
- glossy and dull prints of animals: dogs, cats, foxes, raccoons, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Boat set and crowd from "Showboat", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
- "China Sea", Clark Gable, Jean Harlow, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Letter dated 1954, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- June's promotion to Sgt. 1st Class, Signal Corps, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Clippings of advertisement for movie "Arrowsmith", ca. 1932 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Galley proof for "Filmdom's Famous Five", ca. 1957 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Brochure promoting Biblical film "The Day of Triumph", with accompany note, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Certificate mounted on wooden plaques, including certificates of nomination for award from Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences (1932, 1935, 1957), and certificate of membership in American Society of Cinematographers (1927), 1932-1957 (Box 1)
- Matted portrait of Ray June, 1940 (Map-case Folder 1)
- Portrait montage titled "Nancy Goes to Rio With 'Pop'", with photos of June, crewmen (?) and movie stars as the heads of the figures, n.d. (Map-case Folder 1)
- Oversized photo mounted on cardboard showing Mary Pickford and other girls on balcony, camera and sound crew on left, Pickford superimposed on right (back of cardboard is labeled "Secrets"), n.d. (Map-case Folder 1)
  -also on back is a charcoal drawing of a man and woman in a study, possible story board?